Guide to the Benjamin Fondane Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Benjamin Fondane papers
1912-1943
GEN MSS 750
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
1.67
(5 boxes)
The papers document the life and writing of poet and philosopher Benjamin Fondane. Writings include holograph manuscripts of approximately 650 poems, 55 works of prose and 9 playscripts. Prose writings consist chiefly of holograph drafts of short untitled essays or notes (some fragmentary) on topics related to poetry and philosophy. Also included is a holograph draft of Fondane's first book Tagaduinta lui Petru (1918). Poems consist of holograph drafts of original poems and translations, some titled, others untitled. While most of the writings are undated, they appear to date from before 1923, the year Fondane emigrated to France. Correspondence (incoming and outgoing) is with Fondane's sisters Lina and Rodica Wechsler, other family members, and the journal Hatikvah. Other papers include a catalog of the avant garde theater group Insula, which Fondane co-founded. Material is chiefly in Romanian; some correspondence is in French.
Fondane, Benjamin, 1898-1944
Associated Materials
Printed material received with the collection ( Poezii, Bucureşti 1978, and issues of the journal Hatikvah ) was removed for separate cataloging and can be accessed by searching the library's online catalog.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Ubu Gallery on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund, 2002.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Existence and Location of Copies
The collection is also available on microfilm.
Benjamin Fondane, 1898-1944
Benjamin Fondane, Romanian-French Symbolist poet and philosopher, born Benjamin Wechsler, 1898 in Iaşi, Romania and died 1944 in Auschwitz-Birkenau.
Scope and Contents
The papers document the life and writing of poet and philosopher Benjamin Fondane. Writings include holograph manuscripts of approximately 650 poems, 55 works of prose and 9 playscripts. Prose writings consist chiefly of holograph drafts of short untitled essays or notes (some fragmentary) on topics related to poetry and philosophy. Also included is a holograph draft of Fondane's first book Tagaduinta lui Petru (1918). Poems consist of holograph drafts of original poems and translations, some titled, others untitled. While most of the writings are undated, they appear to date from before 1923, the year Fondane emigrated to France. Correspondence (incoming and outgoing) is with Fondane's sisters Lina and Rodica Wechsler, other family members, and the journal Hatikvah. Other papers include a catalog of the avant garde theater group Insula, which Fondane co-founded. Material is chiefly in Romanian; some correspondence is in French.
Arrangement
Organized into two series: I. Writings, 1912-1923. II. Correspondence and Other Papers, 1912-1943.
Romanian literature; Romanian literature -- Jewish authors; Romanian poetry; Dadaism; Symbolism; Poets; Fondane, Benjamin, 1898-1944; Wechsler, Lina; Wechsler, Rodica; Hatikvah: publicatie zionista bilunara; Insula (Theater group)
- Writings, 1912-1923; Series I; 1.46; (4 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Organized by type of material
  - Prose, undated; 90 (Box 1)
  - Tagaduinta lui Peter, draft, 1918 (Box 1)
  - Poems, undated; 85 (Box 2)
  - Poems, undated; 33 (Box 3)
  - Poems, undated; 9 (Box 4)
  - Poetry (notebooks), 1913-1914, undated; 16 (Box 4)
  - Notes, undated (Box 4)
  - Playscripts, 1916; 4 (Box 4)
- Correspondence and Other Papers, 1912-1943; Series II; 0.21; (1 box)
  Correspondence is arranged roughly chronologically. Other papers are filed after correspondence.
  - Correspondence, 1909-1913 (Box 5)
    Scope and Contents
    Chiefly to and from Lina Wechsler.
  - Correspondence, 1914-1915, undated (Box 5)
    Includes Rodica Wechsler and Hatikvah.
  - Correspondence, undated (Box 5)
  - Correspondence, 1924-1930 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence, 1931-1934 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence, 1935 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence, 1936 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence, 1937 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence, 1938 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence, 1939 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence, 1940 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence, 1941-1943 (Box 5)
  - School records, 1909-1910 (Box 5)
  - Catalog of Insula, 1922-1923; 2 (Box 5)
  - Address book, undated (Box 5)